Guide to the Henry Lewis Stimson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Speeches, Writings, Statements, 1888-1975; Series III
  - Speeches
    - "The Issues in the Far East," notes and first outline for a talk at Saybrook College, Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut, 1934 November 19 (Box 182, Folder 1)
    - Remarks at the Council on Foreign Relations at the presentation of British and foreign State Papers, 1934 November 26 (Box 182, Folder 2)
    - Outline for speech, American Policy in Latin America (Box 182, Folder 3)
    - Outline for speech, Peace Problems in the World Today (Box 182, Folder 3)
    - "Peace Problems of Europe Today," notes for talk at Andover, 1934 December 3 (Box 182, Folder 4)
    - Remarks before the Conference on Crime at Constitution Hall, Washington, DC, 1934 December 10 (Box 182, Folder 5)
    - "Neutrality and War Prevention," before the 29th Annual Meeting of the American Society of International Law, Washington, DC, printed copy, 1935 April 26 (Box 182, Folder 6)
    - "Neutrality and Moral Leadership," a radio address, reprinted in the New York Herald Tribune as "Our Arms Embargo", 1935 October 23 (Box 182, Folder 7)
    - Address to Yale Alumni Program from Washington, DC, 1936 February 21 (Box 182, Folder 8)
    - Manuscript of speech written for the Economics Club, but noted as not used, 1936 November 28 (Box 182, Folder 9)
    - Memorial to Elihu Root delivered at the Century Association, final copy, draft, and notes, 1937 April 27 (Box 182, Folder 10)
    - Remarks at the graduation exercises of Phillips Academy, 1937 June 18 (Box 182, Folder 11)
    - Radio address regarding appeal of the Red Cross for aid to China, 1938 February 4 (Box 182, Folder 12)
    - Remarks before the Hardware Manufacturers' Statistical Association, 1938 April 28 (Box 182, Folder 13)
    - Addresss at Hamilton College, 1938 June 13 (Box 182, Folder 14)
    - "Preserve American Security by Repealing the Embargo," a radio address, 1939 October 5 (Box 182, Folder 15)
    - "Preserve American Security by Repealing the Embargo," preliminary notes for and first, second, and third drafts of a radio address, 1939 October 5 (Box 182, Folder 16-17)
    - Address to the Graduating Class of Phillips Academy, Andover, 1940 June 14 (Box 182, Folder 18)
    - Outline for talk at Yale Commencement regarding military training, 1940 June 17 (Box 182, Folder 19)
    - "America's Interest in the British Navy," a radio address broadcast from New Haven, Connecticut, 1940 June 18 (Box 182, Folder 20)
    - "The Relations of Labor to National Defense" address to the convention of the American Federation of Labor, New Orleans, 1940 November 18 (Box 182, Folder 21)
    - Speech to Conference of Public Relations Officers, 1941 March 11 (Box 182, Folder 22)
    - Notes for speech to supply officers regarding administration on Lend-Lease, 1941 March 17 (Box 182, Folder 23)
    - Radio address for Army Day Program, 1941 April 5 (Box 182, Folder 24)
    - Address at Meeting of the National Conference of United Service Organizations, Washington, DC, 1941 April 17 (Box 182, Folder 25)
    - Radio address regarding War in Europe, final copy, 1941 May 6 (Box 182, Folder 26)
    - Radio address: preliminary outline, suggested draft, and first draft, 1941 May 6 (Box 182, Folder 27)
    - Radio address: second and third drafts, 1941 May 6 (Box 182, Folder 28)
    - Radio address: fourth draft, 1941 May 6 (Box 182, Folder 29)
    - Radio address regarding the War in Europe, fourth draft with final corrections, 1941 May 6 (Box 182, Folder 30)
    - Address at the Graduation Exercises at the U.S. Military Academy, West Point, New York, 1941 June 11 (Box 182, Folder 31)
    - Address to the Graduating Class at West Point, preliminary outline, first and second drafts, 1941 June 11 (Box 182, Folder 32)
    - Address at the Graduating Exercises at the Untied States Military Academy, West Point, New York, third draft with final corrections, 1941 June 11 (Box 182, Folder 33)
    - Radio address on extension of the term of military service, 1941 August 15 (Box 182, Folder 34)
    - Radio address on extension of the term of service for Reserve Officers, National Guardsmen, and selectees, outline and one draft only, 1941 August 15 (Box 182, Folder 35)
    - Drafts and suggestions by others for radio address, 1941 August 15 (Box 182, Folder 36)
    - Address on the American Red Cross Roll Call radio program, draft and final copy, 1941 November 11 (Box 182, Folder 37)
    - Address at the Meeting of the Inter-American Defense Board at the Pan American Union, 1942 March 30 (Box 183, Folder 1)
    - Address at the Harvard University Alumni Luncheon, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1942 June 11 (Box 183, Folder 2)
    - Remarks in accepting Roosevelt Medal at Theodore Roosevelt House, 1942 October 27 (Box 183, Folder 3)
    - Christmas Greeting to Fellow Workers in the War Department, 1942 December 24 (Box 183, Folder 4)
    - Remarks at Conference with the Council of Bishops of the Methodist Church, printed copy only, 1943 February 23 (Box 183, Folder 5)
    - Radio address, "The Size of the Army", 1943 March 9 (Box 183, Folder 6)
    - Radio address opening "Back the Attack"`, 1943 September 10 (Box 183, Folder 7)
    - Radio address during "Army Hour", 1943 November 7 (Box 183, Folder 8)
    - Transcript of extemporaneous talk at presentation of the Howland Prize to Sir John Dill at Yale University, 1944 February 16 (Box 183, Folder 9)
    - Address before the Annual Meeting, American Society of Newspaper Editors, 1944 April 22 (Box 183, Folder 10)
    - Radio address on return from Europe, 1944 July 25 (Box 183, Folder 11)
    - Radio statement for the opening of the Army at War exhibit for the Sixth War Bond Drive, 1944 October 11 (Box 183, Folder 12)
    - "The Returning Soldier," remarks at a meeting called by the Education and Information Divison, 1944 October 16 (Box 183, Folder 13)
    - Radio address regarding National Service Legislation, 1945 February 18 (Box 183, Folder 14)
    - Remarks at ceremonies celebrating the third anniversary of the Army Service Forces, 1945 March 9 (Box 183, Folder 15)
    - Closing remarks at Women's Conference on Universal Military Training, 1945 April 26 (Box 183, Folder 16)
    - Remarks of greeting to General Eisenhower at the Pentagon, 1945 June 18 (Box 183, Folder 17)
    - Remarks at meeting of the Ausable Club, 1945 August 18 (Box 183, Folder 18)
    - Remarks to general staff officers before retiring from office, 1945 September 20 (Box 183, Folder 19)
    - Address at the dinner of the Andover Alumni, 1946 April 25 (Box 183, Folder 20)
    - Notes for speech at Skull and Bones meeting, 1946 June (Box 183, Folder 21)
    - Remarks at meeting of the Ausable Club, 1946 August 17 (Box 183, Folder 22)
    - Notes for speech at the University Club Dinner, 1946 December 18 (Box 183, Folder 23)
    - Remarks at the Squadron A Dinner given in his honor, 1947 January 24 (Box 183, Folder 24)
    - Remarks at Ausable Club Meeting, 1947 August 16 (Box 183, Folder 25)
    - Remarks at his 80th birthday celebration, 1947 September 1 (Box 183, Folder 26)
    - Notes for remarks at Skull and Bones Meeting, New Haven, 1948 June 22 (Box 183, Folder 27)
    - Remarks at meeting of Adirondack Mountain Reserve, 1948 August 21 (Box 183, Folder 28)
  - Writings: General
    - [1880-1883?] (Box 184, Folder 1)
    - "That Buck," in Yale Literary Magazine, 1886 March (Box 184, Folder 2)
    - "Two Men of Italy," in Yale Literary Magazine, 1886 June (Box 184, Folder 2)
    - "Ship Building on Maloney's Lake," in Yale Courant, 1887 (Box 184, Folder 3)
    - "Béranger and France," in Yale Courant, 1887 (Box 184, Folder 3)
    - "Mazzini's Services to Italy", 1888 (Box 184, Folder 4)
    - "The Proposed Glacier National Park," draft of article for the Outlook magazine, 1910 April 8 (Box 184, Folder 5)
    - "The Party's Opportunity," printed in the 29th Assembly District Republican Club Bulletin, 1911 March (Box 184, Folder 6)
    - "The Needs of Our Army," Harper's Weekly, [1911-1912] (Box 184, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript for article on military policy and organization of the army, 1912 (Box 184, Folder 8)
    - "What is the Matter with Our Army," printed in the Independent, 1912 April 18 (Box 184, Folder 9)
    - "Fortifying the Canal," Scientific American, 1912 November 9 (Box 184, Folder 10)
    - "The Defence of the Panama Canal," Scribner's Magazine, 1913 July (Box 184, Folder 11)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times, 1914 January 7 (Box 184, Folder 12)
    - "The New Professor at the Law School," Harvard Alumni Bulletin, 1914 April 1 (Box 184, Folder 13)
    - "Responsible State Government--A Republican Constitutional Program," The Independent, 1914 July 6 (Box 184, Folder 14)
    - "Two Great Political Parties: The Ideal of Self-Government," The Public Ledger, [1914?] (Box 184, Folder 15)
    - "The Military Needs of the United States," issued by the National Security League, Inc., 1915 March 1 (Box 184, Folder 16)
    - "Saving the State's Money," Committee for the Adoption of the Constitution, Publication no. 5, 1915 September (Box 184, Folder 17)
    - "Financial Reforms Proposed in the New Constitution," Guaranty News, 1915 October (Box 184, Folder 18)
    - Letter to the Editor of the New York Times regarding the work of the New York Constitutional Convention, 1915 October 6 (Box 184, Folder 19)
    - Letter to the Editor of the Troy Times regarding the New York State Constitution, 1915 October 19 (Box 184, Folder 20)
    - Letter to the Editor, Milton L'Ecluse, in support of the revised New York State Constitution, 1915 October 21 (Box 184, Folder 21)
    - Letter to the Editor of the Yale News on the subject of military training, [1915-1917?] (Box 184, Folder 22)
    - "Too Small to Fight," Leslie's Weekly, 1916 February 3 (Box 184, Folder 23)
    - Letters to the Editor regarding the army and defense (7), 1916 February-March (Box 184, Folder 24)
    - Letter to the Editor of the New York Times regarding sending the militia to Mexico, 1916 June 25 (Box 184, Folder 25)
    - Letter to the Editor of the New York Times regarding support of Bacon for Senator, 1916 September 15 (Box 184, Folder 26)
    - "Why I Shall Vote for Mr. Hughes," The New Republic, 1916 October 28 (Box 184, Folder 27)
    - "The Record of the Wilson Administration towards the Army," Henry Lewis Stimson assisted by Eric F. Wood, 1916 October (Box 184, Folder 28)
    - Memos for Henry Lewis Stimson from Eric F. Wood in the preparation of The Record of the Wilson Administration Towards the Army, 1916 October (Box 184, Folder 29)
    - Letter to the Editor of the Evening Post regarding U.S. Army, 1916 December 16 (Box 184, Folder 30)
    - Letter to the Editor of the New York Times regarding the National Guard, 1917 January 5 (Box 184, Folder 31)
    - Letter to the Editor of the Evening Sun regarding military service, 1917 January 29 (Box 184, Folder 32)
    - Letter to the Editor of the Phillipia regarding military instruction at Phillips Andover Academy, 1917 March 19 (Box 184, Folder 33)
    - "The Basis for National Military Training," Scribner's Magazine, 1917 April (Box 184, Folder 34)
    - Letter to the editor of the Topeka Capital regarding military service, 1917 April 13 (Box 184, Folder 35)
    - "A National Budget System," World's Work, 1917 (Box 184, Folder 36)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times, "A Defense of General Crowder's Administration of His Office," similar letter to the editor of the Public Ledger, 1919 April 6 (Box 184, Folder 37)
    - Memorial to Theodore Weston, [1919 May 7?] (Box 184, Folder 38)
    - "Artillery in a Quiet Sector," Scribner's Magazine, article and notes, 1919 June (Box 184, Folder 39)
    - Letter to the editor regarding Railway Brotherhoods, 1919 August 6 (Box 184, Folder 40)
    - Letter to the editor of the Long Islander regarding annual Thanksgiving Day frolic, 1919 November 10 (Box 184, Folder 41)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times, "The Best Budget Plan", 1919 December 7 (Box 184, Folder 42)
    - "The Leitch Plan," The Survey, printed copy only, 1919 December 20 (Box 184, Folder 43)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Tribune, "Socialists' Rights" plus notes, 1920 January 16 (Box 184, Folder 44)
    - Letters to the editors of the New York Times and the New York Tribune challenging Dr. Butler's attack on General Wood's campaign, 1920 January 18 (Box 184, Folder 45)
    - Brief: "Forward" for book of stories by Captain Loren C. Grieves, 1920 August 3 (Box 184, Folder 46)
    - Statement for the Evening Post on fiscal policy and appropriations, 1920 September (Box 184, Folder 47)
    - "For Harding and the League," letter to the editor of the New York Tribune commenting on Herbert Parsons' letter of resignation from the Republican Party, 1920 October 21 (Box 184, Folder 48)
    - Letter to the editor regarding New York State Proposition to grant a military bonus, 1920 October 26 (Box 184, Folder 49)
    - Memorial to Winfred Thaxter Denison for the Bar Association, 1920 December (Box 184, Folder 50)
    - "Our Debt of Honor," World's Work, 1921 February (Box 184, Folder 51)
    - "Bonus First or Disabled?," New York Times, 1921 March 6 (Box 184, Folder 52)
    - "No time for Complacency," The World's Work, 1921 April (Box 184, Folder 53)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times regarding candidacy of Judge Andrews, 1921 November 4 (Box 184, Folder 54)
    - Memorial to Winthrop Grant Bushnell, 1921 November 18 (Box 184, Folder 55)
    - Memorial to Theodore Roosevelt, 1921 December 19 (Box 184, Folder 56)
    - "The Cause of High Prices," World's Work, 1922 October (Box 184, Folder 57)
    - Memorial to Candace Wheeler, printed in the Evening Post, 1923 August 6 (Box 184, Folder 58)
    - "Introduction" to one of the volumes of Theodore Roosevelt's collected works, The Foes of Our Household, 1923 December 26 (Box 184, Folder 59)
    - Letter to the editor of the Washington Post regarding Soldiers' Bonus, 1924 May 20 (Box 185, Folder 1)
    - Letters to the editor of the New York Times regarding Herbert Parsons (Box 185, Folder 2)
    - Statement for the New York Tribune regarding New York Constitutional amendment regarding state debt, 1925 October 1 (Box 185, Folder 3)
    - Letters to the editor of the New York Times and the Long Islander regarding New York Constitutional amendments, 1925 October 28 (Box 185, Folder 4)
    - Letters to the editor of the New York Herald Tribune regarding New York constitutional amendment, 1925 October 29 (Box 185, Folder 5)
    - Memorial to Herbert Parsons for Bar Association, plus notes, 1926 March 25 (Box 185, Folder 6)
    - "First-Hand Impressions of the Philippine Problem," Saturday Evening Post, 1927 March 17 (Box 185, Folder 7)
    - "Future Philippine Policy Under the Jones Act," Foreign Affairs, printed copy and original outline, 1927 April (Box 185, Folder 8)
    - "American Policy in Nicaragua," Saturday Evening Post, galley proof only, 1927 October (Box 185, Folder 9)
    - "Why I am a Republican," New York Times, article and draft, 1932 October 30 (Box 185, Folder 10)
    - "Bases of American Foreign Policy during the Past Four Years," Foreign Affairs, 1933 April (Box 185, Folder 11)
    - "Are the Powers of the President Improving the American Government," typed copy of article from the Congressional Digest, 1933 November (Box 185, Folder 12)
    - "Nationalism and Internationalism," The World Today, an Encyclopaedia Britannica supplement, 1935 February (Box 185, Folder 13)
    - "The Dangers of Neutrality," letter to the editor of the New York Times, printed final copy and draft, 1935 October 11 (Box 185, Folder 14)
    - "Neutrality and War Prevention," The Forum, reprint of Apr 26, 1935 speech with an addendum, 1935 November (Box 185, Folder 15)
    - "To the Lady in Brown," article for the centennial number of the Yale Literary Magazine, 1936 (Box 185, Folder 16)
    - To the editor of the Baltimore Sun regarding the Supreme Court, 1937 February 6 (Box 185, Folder 17)
    - "Foreword" for the International Quarterly, 1937 March (Box 185, Folder 18)
    - Memorial of Elihu Root, Yearbook of the Association of the Bar, New York City, 1937 June (Box 185, Folder 19)
    - "The Crisis at Our Western Gate," letter to the editor of the New York Times regarding the Far East, manuscript, outlines and notes, 1937 October 6 (Box 185, Folder 20)
    - Letter to the editor of the Long Islander regarding the candidacy of Arthur Kreutzer for town supervisor, includes notes, 1937 October 18 (Box 185, Folder 21)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times opposing the Ludlow Resolution for a National Referendum on a Declaration of War, 1937 December 21 (Box 185, Folder 22)
    - Research material for letter to the editor of the New York Times opposing the Ludlow Resolution, 1937 December 21 (Box 185, Folder 23)
    - Draft of foreword to Edward W. Evans' America in Search of Security, [1938 July 15] (Box 185, Folder 24)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times supporting the candidacy of John Lord O'Brien for Congressman, 1938 October 21 (Box 185, Folder 25)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times regarding the Labor Relations Act, 1938 November 3 (Box 185, Folder 26)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times regarding the embargo of arms to Spain, printed copies only, 1939 January 24 (Box 185, Folder 27)
    - "The Basis of an Affirmative Foreign Policy Today," letter to the editor of the New York Times, 1939 March 6 (Box 185, Folder 28)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times favoring the repeal of the arms embargo, 1939 September 15 (Box 185, Folder 29)
    - Memorial to Dr. John Rogers for the Boone and Crockett Club, 1939 December (Box 185, Folder 30)
    - "Legislation to Prohibit War Exports to Japan," letter to the editor of the New York Times, 1940 January 11 (Box 185, Folder 31)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Herald-Tribune regarding support for allies and military training, 1940 June 10 (Box 185, Folder 32)
    - "Tribute to the War Records of Our Members," The University Club, printed copy only, 1946 (Box 185, Folder 33)
    - "The Bomb and the Opportunity," Harper's Magazine, printed copy only, 1946 March (Box 185, Folder 34)
    - "The Nuremberg Trial: Landmark in Law," Foreign Affairs, 1947 January (Box 186, Folder 1)
    - "The Decision to Use the Bomb," Harper's Magazine, 1947 February (Box 186, Folder 2)
      General
      See also: box 186, folder 3A.
    - "The Decision to Use the Bomb," in Harper's Magazine, outline and manuscript with annotations, 1947 February (Box 186, Folder 3)
    - Cary, Otis, "The Sparing of Kyoto-Mr. Stimson's 'Pet City'," Japan Quarterly, 1975 October-December (Box 186, Folder 3A)
      See also: box 172, folder 18.
      See also: box 188, folder 12.
      See also: box 186, folder 2.
      See also: diaries, volume LI, page 149 (1 June 1945).
    - "The Challenge to Americans," in Foreign Affairs, printed copy only, 1947 October (Box 186, Folder 4)
    - "The Atomic Bomb and Peace with Russia," in Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, printed copy only, reprint of a chapter from On Active Service, 1948 August (Box 186, Folder 5)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times regarding Senator McCarthy, 1950 March 27 (Box 186, Folder 6)
  - Writings: Far Eastern Crisis
    - Typed memos and outlines used in preparation of the Far Eastern Crisis., 1935 August-1936 February (Box 187, Folder 1-2)
    - Notes for the Far Eastern Crisis based on White Paper Conditions in Manchuria sent to Senate, Jan 27, 1932, covering period of Sep-Nov 1931 (Box 187, Folder 3)
    - Handwritten notes, sequences of events Nov 1931-Mar 1932, material for the Far Eastern Crisis, including summary on embargo, Jan 7, 1932 note to Japan, and attempt to invoke the 9-Power Treaty (Box 187, Folder 4)
    - Copy of diary entries regarding Manchuria, reference for the Far Eastern Crisis, 1931 September 19-1933 March 2 (Box 187, Folder 5)
    - Summary of cables regarding Far East, used as reference material in writing the Far Eastern Crisis, 1931 August 20-October 13 (Box 187, Folder 6)
    - Summary of Hornbeck's memoranda for period of Sep 19, 1931-Dec 23, 1931 for reference on Far Eastern Crisis (Box 187, Folder 7)
    - Copies of cables to Dawes, reference for the Far Eastern Crisis, 1931 November 19-21 (Box 187, Folder 8)
    - Compilation of State Department cables regarding the Far East for the period Jan 22, 1932-Feb 10, 1932, reference for the Far Eastern Crisis (Box 187, Folder 9)
    - Reference material for the Far Eastern Crisis, handwritten copies of special cables from Nelson Johnson regarding Shanghai situation, 1932 February (Box 187, Folder 10)
    - Reference material for the Far Eastern Crisis, 1932 January-March (Box 187, Folder 11)
    - Handwritten notes for Far Eastern Crisis regarding Lytton Report and reactions to it, 1932 October-December (Box 187, Folder 12)
    - Copies of correspondence between State Department and U.S. Delegation in Geneva regarding the British (Sir John Simon) reaction to situation in Japan, used as reference material for Far Eastern Crisis, 1932 December 9-14 (Box 187, Folder 13)
    - Copies of correspondence between Sir John Simon and Norman Davis, reference material for Far Eastern Crisis, 1932 December 13-14 (Box 187, Folder 14)
    - Unidentified notes used in preparation of Far Eastern Crisis (Box 187, Folder 15)
    - Notes made on articles read regarding Japan, reference material for Far Eastern Crisis, 1934 June (Box 187, Folder 16)
    - Address by Dewitt Clinton Poole to the Conference on the Cause and Cure of War, reference for Far Eastern Crisis, 1935 January 24 (Box 187, Folder 17)
    - Manchuria, a report of the Commission of Enquiry appointed by the League of Nations, 1932 October 1 (Box 187, Folder 18)
    - Mailing list for the Far Eastern Crisis (Box 187, Folder 19)
  - Writings: On Active Service
    - Index of statements made by Henry Lewis Stimson in interviews with Winnacker and Bundy in preparation of On Active Service (Box 188, Folder 1)
    - Interviews with Bundy
      - "Political Outline," pp. 31-47, includes the preliminary outlines, 1946 May 10 (Box 188, Folder 2)
      - Pp. 48-62, regarding religion, education, college life, 1946 May 29 (Box 188, Folder 3)
      - Part I, pp. 63-74, regarding politics, home, clubs, exercise in New York, life on Long Island, National Guard, the 3rd Battle of Bull Run, 1946 May 29 (Box 188, Folder 4)
      - Part I, pp. 85-95, regarding the Philippines (Box 188, Folder 5)
      - Part II, pp. 96-100, regarding law practice, prohibition, 1946 May 30 (Box 188, Folder 6)
      - Parts I and II, pp. 101-114, regarding historic law on basic moral problems, Russia, Justice Holmes, Taft, Woman Suffrage, Experiences in Order of Importance, State Department vs. War Department, Congress, 1946 June 4 (Box 188, Folder 7)
      - Regarding Pre-overlord, S-1, future of Germany, discipline in the army, District Attorney's Dinner, 1946 June 5, 13 (Box 188, Folder 8)
      - Pp. 121-131, regarding the State Department, civil affairs, Hull, MacArthur, the navy, Admiral Pratt, black chamber--centralized government intelligence, 1946 June 14 (Box 188, Folder 9)
      - Pp. 132-148, regarding framework of the book, campaign of 1910, theories on government, executive budget, 1946 June 18 (Box 188, Folder 10)
      - Pp. 149-166, regarding the War Department, Army Pearl Harbor Board, friends in Army, civilian experts, Ordinance Department, colored problems, Japanese relocation, 1946 July 8 (Box 188, Folder 11)